Julius Braunthal Papers ARCH.00111
International Institute of Social History
Julius Braunthal Papers
1891-1972
ARCH00111
Braunthal, Julius
4 Meters
International Institute of Social History Cruquiusweg 31 1019 AT Amsterdam Nederland ask@iisg.nl URL:
Biographical Note
Born in Vienna 1891, died in Teddington, Great Britain 1972; writer, active in the international social democratic movement; member of the executive committees of the Sozialdemokratische Arbeiterpartei in Österreich (SDAP) and the Republikanischer Schutzbund; imprisoned and tried for high treason in 1934, expelled from Austria in 1935; lived in Belgium 1935-1936; settled in Great Britain in 1938; editor of the Tribune from 1937, the International Socialist Forum 1938-1948; secretary of the Committee of the International Socialist Conferences (COMISCO) 1949-1951, secretary-general of the Socialist International (SI) 1951-1956; author of the `History of the International' in three volumes, published between 1961-1971.
Acquisition
Papers donated to the IISH by Julius Braunthal in 1970; with accruals from his widow Tini Braunthal in the period 1971-1975.
Geschiedenis archiefbeheer
Het archief werd door Braunthal in 1970 aan het IISG geschonken. In de loop van 1971 werd het overgebracht. Braunthal had het plan bij de inventarisatie van zijn archief te assisteren. Helaas overleed hij op 28 april 1972.
Zijn weduwe Ernestine (Tini) Braunthal stuurde in de jaren na zijn dood nog enige waardevolle aanvullingen aan brieven en ander materiaal, die aan het archief werden toegevoegd.
Content
Documents on his trial, his family and their emigration 1934-1946, and biographical notes; correspondence with Austrian, British and other socialists 1891-1972, including Rafail Abramovič, Friedrich Adler and Karl Kautsky, on the International Socialist Forum 1941-1948 and correspondence issued as secretary-general of the Socialist International 1950-1956; radio talks for the BBC 1939-1943, 1948-1949; manuscripts of published and unpublished books, articles, lectures, speeches, notably on the political situation and socialism in Austria, Germany, Israel, Asia; notes and other documents relating to his biographies on Otto Bauer (including the manuscript) and Victor and Friedrich Adler; correspondence on his publications and speeches, and press clippings of reviews; some other documents and press clippings on various subjects; some printed material.
Raadpleging
Not restricted
INLEIDING
Julius Braunthal werd op 5 mei 1891 in Wenen geboren.
Hij bezocht daar de lagere school en voortgezet onderwijs en op 14-jarige leeftijd ging hij in de leer voor boekbinder.
In 1905 sloot hij zich aan bij de socialistische jeugdbeweging en werd een jaar later voorzitter van een van de districtsafdelingen in Wenen. Otto Bauer werd zijn mentor en de man die hem stimuleerde tot journalistieke aktiviteiten. In 1912 werd hij redakteur bij de socialistische krant "Volksstimme" in Warnsdorf (Bohemen).
Bij het uitbreken van de Eerste Wereldoorlog wird hij opgeroepen militaire dienst te verrichten bij een artillerie-regiment van het Oostenrijks-Hongaarse leger. Na de oorlog werde hij adjutant van Julius Deutsch de staatssekretaris van Defensie van 1918 tot 1920.
Hierna kwamen zijn publicistische aktiviteiten tot bloei. Hij schreef regelmatig in bladen als "Arbeiter Zeitung", "Der Kampf" en "Das Kleine Blatt".
In 1922 was hij lid van een hulpmissie van de International Federation of Trade Unions naar Georgië (Sowjet Unie).
Hij was lid van het Uitvoerend Comité van de Oostenrijkse Sociaal-Democratische Partij ( S.P.Ö.) tot 1934 het jaar waarin hij werd gearresteerd en gevangen gezet na de staatsgreep van Dollfuss. Na een jaar werd hij vrijgelaten en moest het land verlaten. Hij leefde van 1935 tot 1936 in België en emigreerde daarna naar Engeland. In 1937 werd hij redakteur van de "Tribune".
Friedrich Adler nodigde hem in 1938 uit om medewerker te worden op het sekretariaat van de Labour and Socialist International (L.S.I.) te Brussel.
De Tweede Wereldoorlog dwong hem terug te keren naar Engeland. Hij richtte in 1941 samen met o.a. Harold Laski en Louis de Brouckère het maandblad " International Socialist Forum" op, waarvan hij tot 1948 chefredakteur was.
Vanaf 1946 was hij aktief betrokken bij de voorbereidingen voor de heroprichting van de Socialistische Internationale (S.I.). Hij werd sekretaris van de COMISCO en daarna sekretaris-general van de S.I. te Londen van 1951 tot 1956. Spoedig na zijn aftreden als sekretaris maakte hij een reis door Azië, gaf lezingen en legde kontakten met socialistische partijen daar. In die tijd begon hij ook aan het schrijven van zijn grote werk "Die Geschichte der Internationale" dat in 1971 klaar kwam.
Belangrijk waren zijn verdiensten als bestuurslid van het Internationaal Instituut voor Sociale Geschiedenis (I.I.S.G.) met name zijn bemoeienissen met het verkrijgen van belangrijke archief- of bibliotheekaanwinsten o.a. de archieven van Robert Grimm en Bruno Misèfari. Op zijn tachtigste verjaardag kreeg hij van de Oostenrijkse regering de honoraire titel van professor.
Braunthal overleed in Teddington (Middlesex) op 28 april 1972.
Julius Braunthal trouwde in 1917 met de Weense Ernestine (Tini) Gernreich. Ze kregen twee zonen Frederick Gustav Braunthal en Thomas Otto Braunthal.
Voor verdere biografische gegevens zie:
Manfred Ackermann, Julius Braunthal. Ein Leben dem Sozialismus geweiht.
J. Braunthal, Auf der Suche nach dem Millenium.
Archief J. Braunthal, Nr. 9.
INDEX
betreffende nr. 19-20, 92-100, 103-106, 136-143, 145-148, 150-166, 167, 169-189, 280-284, 290-294
A
Aa, H. 178
Abramovitch, R. 139, 173, 177-180
Abramsky, C. 184
Ackermann, M. 176, 178, 185-186, 188, 294
Adama van Scheltema, A. 20, 136, 141-142, 154, 156,
174-175, 177, 179-180, 187-188
Adler, Friedrich 20, 136-137, 290, 316, 334
Adler, D. 179
Adler, Victor 316-318, 334
Adler, K. 19, 20, 153, 158, 290
Adolph, H.J.L. 180
Aggarwala, R.N. 146
Almon, A. 180
Allerdt, H. 175
American Committee for Cultural Freedom 173
Anders, K. 107, 174, 176, 185
Andersen, Alsing 176
Andréas, Bert 186
Antonioletti, G. 157
Arani Verlags GmbH 174
Arbeit und Wirtschaft 172
Arbeiter Zeitung 141, 172-173, 186, 290, 294
Asian Socialist Conference 147, 173, 302, 366
Aspling, S. 176
Attlee, C.R. 173
Augsten, A. 138
Ausch, J. 182
Ausch, K. 19, 103, 110, 137, 141-142, 148, 172-175, 177-188, 294
Azzaroni, B. 160
B
Backer Verlag 172
Bahne, Siegfried 186
Balabanoff, Angelica 111
Banning, W. 111, 142
Baratz, J. 137
Barents, Joseph 137
Bargil, M. 173
Barkatt, Reuven 148, 176, 184, 186, 188, 189
Barrie Group of Publishers 184
Batelli, F. 148, 167, 174, 289, 291
Ba Than 147
Battara, P. 151, 154
Bauer, J. 111, 137-139
Bauer, Otto 288
Bax, A. 155
B.B.C. 136
Beales, H.L. 154
Beatrice Webb Trustees 173
Beauclerck, C. 103
Becu, O. 155
Beier, E. 180
Belgische Radio en Televisie 183
Bellamy, J.M. 185, 188-189
Berlstein, A. 181
Bernard, Vilhelm 186
Bibliographia Judaica 183
Bienenfeld, F.R. 177
Blase, A. 289, 291
Blau, P. 185-186
Blit, S. 172
Blum, M.E. 180
Blumenberg, Werner 151, 153-154, 156, 180-181, 289
Boberg, S. 154
Bolle, M.C. 136
Bönisch, F. 103
Bor, M. 187
Botz, G. 185
Boudin, L. 19
Bourdet, Y. 182-185
Braatoy, B. 157
Bracht 141
Bracke, Alexandre 19
Brahm, Heinz 185, 187, 293
Brailsford, Henry Noel 104, 149, 178
Brandt, Willy 137
Brauer, M. 154, 176
Braun, I. 157
Braun, Otto 19
Braunthal, Alfred 19, 136-137, 139-140, 153, 155, 176, 178, 180-181, 184, 186
Braunthal, Fred 182
Braunthal, G. 139, 175-178, 181, 184-187
Braunthal, H. 171
Breit, V. 180, 289
British Museum 170, 173, 174
Brockway, Fenner 137, 156, 160, 176, 185
Broido, E. 148
Bruegel, J.W. 178, 180
Brügel, W. 136, 183
Buckhurst Hill Labour Party 136
Bund Archives of the Jewish Labor Movement 289
Bund Verlag GmbH Köln-Deutz 183
Bung, H. 173
Buset, M. 104
Bush, J. 138
Bush, S. 142
C
Cambridge University Press 185
Carlebach, J. 187
Carthy, Albert E. 152-153, 156-158, 159, 161, 163, 174, 177, 289
Cemach, Alexander I. 136
Centenaire de la Fondation del'Internationale Socialiste 181
Centre for Contemporary Socialist Thought 184
Centre for Labour and Social Studies 181
Children and Youth Aliyah Committee for Great Britain 177, 181-184
Ciolkosz, A. 178, 181-184, 187
Clark, R.W. 186
Codignola, T. 136-137, 139, 167
Cole, G.D.H. 154, 173, 287
Cole, H.T.D. 176
Cole, Margaret 154-155, 157, 185-188, 278
Collick, P. 155-156
Collins, H. 180-181, 186, 293
Combate 177
COMISCO 136
"Commentary" 176
Communist Party of India 147
Cie. général transatlantique Ltd. 175
Consolidated Tours Inc. 175
Corsi, A. 151, 167
Cosmo Enterprises 174
Costello, D. 187-188
D
Daily Herald 153
Damjanovic, P. 177
Dan, L. 154, 158
Danneberg, Gertrud 154
Das, B. 143
Davar 148
Day, Alan 186, 188, 293
Dekock, J. 187-188
Derndarsky, M. 188
Deutsch, Julius 103, 180-181
Deutsche Akademie für Sprache und Dichtung 174
Deutsche Welle 294
Deutscher, Isaak 171
Deutschkron, I. 178, 181-185, 188
Dokumentationsarchiv des Oesterreichischen Widerstandes 183, 188
Donneur, A.P. 184
Dodge, P. 173
E
Eastwood, R. 178
Ebel, C. 139
Eckert, Georg 160-161, 183, 187
Editions du Seuil 184
Eggenberger, M. 173
Eichler, Willi 140, 153-155, 160, 184, 186, 188
Eisner, F. 153
Elias, A. 290
Ellenbogen, Wilhelm 136-137
Elliot, S. 178
Elstein, D. 179
Engle, J.B. 176
Erben, W. 180
Erlander, Tage Fritjof 178
Estrin, S. 141, 173-176, 180-181, 184
L'Etang, W.L. 156
Etudes et Documentation Internationales 188
Europa Verlags-AG 184-186, 290
Europäische Perspektiven 182
Europe Left 182
Evalenko, R. 138
F
Fabian Society 176, 183
Fackelträger Verlag 289
Faravelli, G. 151
Ferrari, V. 173
Feuer, L.S. 185
Flesch, F. 136
Florence, R. 184
Florida, Atlantic University 183
Ford, P. 293
" Foreign Affairs" 176
Forum 184
Frank, L. 158, 173-175, 181, 290
Frank, W. 138
Freeden, L.M. 148
Frei, B. 178, 180
Freyh, R. 139-140
Friedrich Ebert Stiftung 182, 188
Friends of the Hebrew University of Jerusalem 140, 178, 181, 183, 185-188
Friends of Socialist Commentary 173
Fromm, Erich 157
G
Gaitskell, D. 180, 187
Gaitskell, Hugh 143, 167, 173
" Geist und Tat" 179
Glagov, S. 180-181
Gleissberg, G. 136-137, 141
Gmür, F. 155
Golan, C. 188
Goldmann, H.F. 188
Goldschneider, P. 173
Gollancz, R. 180
Gollancz, Victor 19, 174, 180
Gopalan, A.K. 147
Gottfurcht, Hans 178, 181
Gottschalk, A. 182
Grimm, J. 153, 176
Grimm, Robert 151, 153
Grossmann, S. 19
Grumbach, Salomon 139
Gruppe Oesterreichischer Sozialisten in Buenos Aires 139
Gruppe Sozialistischer Verleger und Buchhändler 289
Gulick, Charles A. 180
Gurland, A.R.L. 142
H
Haag, J. 188
Haas, K. 180-181, 183
Hacker, W. 141
Hagen, A. 155-156
Hahner, J.E. 186
Haikar Haoved 148
Halasi, A.B. 174
Hale, L. 176
Halperin, B. 138
Haluan 146
Hannak, Jacques 262
Hannoversche Druck- und Verlags GmbH 293
Hannoversche Presse 172
Haralambiev, I. 186
Harcavi, I. 148, 175
Harper, O. 151
Harrison, R. 184, 186
Harvard University 185
Healy, Denis 182
Heidenheimer 138
Heine, Friedrich 138, 140, 142-143, 159-160, 173-174, 177, 181, 189, 289, 291, 293-294
Heinz, G. 154, 291
Heinz, Karl 178-179, 181-184, 186, 176
Held, A. 19
Helmer, Oskar 103
Hentschel, F. 181
Herlitzka, E.K. 290, 293
Hermes, G. 179
Hertz, Paul 156
Heusmann, R. 174
Heuss, E.L. 180
Heuss, Theodor 139, 180
Hill, G. 173
Hinden, R. 167
Hine, R. 182
Hirsch, Hans en Bettina 20, 103, 106
Hirsch, H. 184-185
Hirsch, J. 154-155
Hitachdut 148, 137, 178
Hodges, S. 20, 140, 173-174, 176-178, 180-186
Hoegger, R. 180
Hofbauer, Josef 19
Hohenbalken, P. 184
Holanbek, J. 173
Hook, S. 137
Hoover Institution 291
Hornik, L. 185
Horrabin, F. 136, 154, 173
Hoselitz, B.F. 175
Hrdlitschka, W. 181
Huhn, Willy 138
Humbert-Droz, J. 151, 154
Huysmans, Camille 157
I
Illner, E. 177
Indian Committee for Cultural Freedom 146
Indian Council of World Affairs 146
Ingersoll, F.J. 185
Institut für Sozialgeschichte Braunschweig 182-183, 187
Institute of International Labor Research Inc. 176
Institut Hjalmar Branting 173
I.I.S.G. 147, 150-165, 179
International Confederation of Free Trade Unions 174, 177
International Federation of Textile Workers' Association 155
International Jewish Labor Bund 289
International Society for Socialist Studies 176
International Trade Secretariats 155
International Transport Workers' Federation 155-156
International Union of Socialist Youth 173-174
Internationale Graphische Föderation 155
Internationaler Metallarbeiter Bund 155
Israel Labour Party 148, 173-175, 182, 186, 188, 289
J
Jaksch, Wenzel 176
" Janata" 177, 187
Janitschek, H. 185-187
Jemnitz, J. 187
Jenschik, Ant. 136, 142
Jerusalem, A. 174-175, 177, 180
Jerusalem, E. 137, 174-176
Jewish Agency for Israel 186
Jewish National Fund 186
Jewish Vanguard 143, 148, 176, 180
Jochmann, Rosa 141, 166, 184
John Clark Memorial Fund 182
Joint Palestine Appeal 186-187
Jolis, A.E. 137
Joll, J. 171, 185, 293
Josephtal 148
K
Kandiah, P. 147
Kandler, F. 139
Karnik, V.B. 146
Károly, S. 174
Kautsky, Benedikt 19, 142, 153
Kautsky, Bettina 181-182, 185
Kautsky, G. 155-157, 177, 181
Kautsky, J.M. 157
Kautsky Jr., Karl 181-184, 186-188, 290, 294
Kautsky, L. 184
Kautsky, M. 157, 176, 181
Kawakami, T. 291, 293
Keller, F.O. 136
Kettler, E. 178, 176
Khalaf, Abbas M. 156
Kilpatrick, W.H. 176
Klein, O.G. 188
"Das Kleine Blatt" 136, 173
Klenner, Fritz 185, 187
Kluge, U. 185
Knoeringen, Waldemar von 160-161
Knöpfmacher, H. 173, 175, 188
Koerner, Th. 173, 103
Koirala, B.P. 146
Kollman, E.C. 179-180
Kommunistische Partei Oesterreichs, ZK der 185
Konzentration GmbH 177, 180-182, 184-188, 289, 291, 293-294
Korakas, M. 174, 176, 177, 180, 186
Korn, I. 175
Körner, R. 187
Kot, S. 138
Koulischer, G. 137
Koulisheff, G. 178
Krane, J. 139
Kreisky, Bruno 182, 188, 290
Kreuzer, F. 290
Kruk, J. 173-174, 177-179
Kubowitzki, A. Leon 136
Kwashi, N.A. 174
L
Labelle, D. 180
Labor Committee to Release Imprisoned Trade Unionists and Democratic Socialists 173, 178
Labor Zionist Organization of America "Poale Zion" 175-176
Labour Party of England 175, 177, 181, 186-187
Laidler, H.W. 154
Lakenbacher, Ernst 141, 180-182, 184, 290
Lakenbacher, P. 184-185
Lall, J. 177, 179
Lamm, H. 185
Landauer, C. 175-179, 154, 181-183, 185, 187, 290
Lanzer, W. 137, 142, 175, 188
Larock, Victor 179
Laski, F. 178
Lauterbach, A. 141, 175, 180-183, 188, 289
Lavon, P. 148
Lazarsfeld, S. 186, 290
League for Industrial Democracy 176
Lebzeltern, G. 188
Ledebour 153
Leichter, Otto 103, 138
Leighton, P. 185
Lemberger, Ernst 19
Leo Baeck Institute 177-179, 182-183, 290
Leser, N. 180-181, 290
Levenberg, Sneier 140-141, 148, 189, 293
Lévy, Louis 19
Lévy, M.L. 175
Levy, R. 186
Lewisohn, I. 175
Lichtheim, George 294
Lie, Haakon 176-177
Lind, P. 154, 290
Lindbom, T. 154
Livny, S. 148
Llopis, R. 154-155
Lloyds Bank Ltd. 182
Löbe, Paul 141, 173
Locker, Berl 148
Loebar, K. 181
Lohia, Rammanohar 142
Löwe, A. 174
Luza, R. 182
M
MacMillan and Co. Ltd. 177
Magaziner, A. 290
Maier, G. 151, 157
Maisel, Karl 181
Maitron, J. 154, 187-188
Majdalani, N. 156
Maleta, A. 188
Mann, Heinrich 189
Mapai 148
Marek, B. 185
Marold, P. 289
Martin, Kingsley 138, 153, 156, 184
Marty, A. 151
Massee, J. 174
Massiczek, A. 182, 186
Matoren, S. 185
Matteotti, Matteo 173
Mattmüller-Keller, M. 180
Maung Maung, U. 146-147
Mayer, B. 174
Mayer, P. 153, 159-160
Mehta, Asoka 177
Meier, E. 151
Meier, Gabrielle 154, 160
Mendelsohn, K. 148, 186
Menon, K. 146-147, 177
Meynell, H. 173-174
Merchav, P. 148
Middleton, James 138, 155, 173
Middleton, L. 181, 184-186
Milford, Peter 181
Millar, Chr. 184
Millar, J.P.M. 137, 178
Miller, S. 178, 180, 185, 187-188, 290
Milton, S. 186
Miners' International Federation 155
Misefari, Pia 160-161, 163-164, 179, 183-184, 186
Mitchell, K. 293
Møller, F. 137
Mollet, G. 136
Mons, R. 183
Montani, D. Ambrosio 153
Moortel, M. van de 155
Moratt, S.H. 147, 148
Morgan, R. 176-180, 289
Morsbach, A. 182
Mösslinger, E. 187
Movement for Colonial Freedom 156-157, 187
Mukkerji, Partha A. 179
N
Nagy, B. 153
Naoroji, Khurshed A.D. 177
Naphtali-Zarak, M. 181
Narayan, Jayaprakash 142, 146
Narmadeshawar Prasad 146
National Campaign for the Abolition of Capital Punishment 178
National Committee for Labor Israel 175
National Council of Labour Colleges 174-177, 179-183, 185-187
National Planning Association 174
National Union of Mineworkers 173
National Union of Tailors and Garment Workers 155
Natsir, M. 147
Naumann-Anders, H. 20
Nebbot, A. 184
Neck, R. 183
Nedzynski, S. 155-156
Nenni, Pietro 154
Nest Verlag GmbH 177-178, 180, 290
Neubauer, H. 179
Neumann, F.L. 137
The New Leader 182
News of the World Ltd. 177
The New Socialist 177
Det Norske Arbeiderparti 177
Nicolaevsky, Boris I. 153, 175
Nicolinacos, M. 179-180
Nimal Karuwatillake 147
Nobs, Ernst 151, 153
Nobs, R. 153
Nordahl 104
Norman Thomas 80th Birthday Committee 181
Nuffield College 188
La Nuova Italia Editrice 140, 142, 167, 183
Nuselovici-Moldavanu 139
O
Oficina Internacional del Trabajo 188
Ollenhauer, Erich 136
Oprecht, H. 19, 153-154, 157, 175
Oschilewski, Walther G. 139, 142
Otto Wels-Gesellschaft 180
P
Paasivirta, J. 148
Pacheco 178
Pankhurst, R. 155
Papanek, Ernst 155, 158, 175-176, 179, 186, 291
Papanek, H. 157, 159
Papernik, O. 182
Partai Kommunist Indonesia 147
Partai Nasional Indonesia 147
Parti Socialiste S.F.I.O. 19, 173
Partha-Sarathi Gupta 187
Partito Socialista Democratico Italiano 173-174, 179
Paul, E. 138
Pedoman Perdjuangan Masjumi 147
Perovic, P. 156, 178
Philipp, Hans 136
Phillips, Morgan 137, 142-143, 154
Pick, W.J. 189
Pinner, H. 148
Piperger, Alois 136, 142, 173, 179-180, 290
Pittermann, Bruno 177, 182, 187
" Plebs" 173-174, 176-181
Poale Zion 148, 181
Pogats, E. 290
Pollak, Marianne 180
Pollak, Oskar 19-20, 103, 137, 172
Pollak, W. 186
Pontillon, R. 151, 178, 289
Porges, G. 185
Posch, Fr. 174
Postal Telegraph and Telephone International 155, 160, 182
Postgate, R. 154, 175
Praja Socialist Party 177, 183
Price, H.H. 185
Probst, Otto 156-157, 172
Proft, G. 139, 167, 173-174, 177, 181, 183-186, 290-291, 293
Pryce, R. 186
Putzrath, Heinz 139-141, 156
Pucciani, O. 177
R
Ragaz, C. 180
Ramanathan, D.R. 156
The Reconstructionist 148
Reichenbach, B. 136
Reiss, A. 148, 183
Renner, Karl 19, 103
Resampa, A. 156
Reventlow, R. 137, 181-185
Richter, A. 182
Riepl, H. 141
Rischin, M. 185
Rocker, F. 153-154
Rolland, H. 160
Rosdolsky, Emmy 163
Rosdolsky, Roman 290
Rosenbach, D. 293
Rosenbach, N. 289
Rosenzweig, S. 179
Rosmer, A. 154-155
Ross Williamson, A. 103
Rothschild, J.A. 140
Rubel, M. 139, 154
Ruijter, A. de 155
Rüter, A.J.C. 19, 150-160
S
Sagher, Mobarak 176, 181
Sailer, E. 181
Sapir, Boris 157, 186-187, 290
Saran, M. 184-185
Sarkar, C. 146, 174, 177
Sastrosatomo, S. 187, 293
Saville, J. 155-156, 158, 160-161, 177, 186, 188
Schärf, Adolf 103, 136-137, 139, 141-142, 172-173, 180
Scherer 174
Schevenels, W. 104
Schiavi, A. 143, 148, 151, 155-157, 167, 176, 179
Schiavi, L. 160, 182
Schlossberg, J. 154, 176
Schmidt-Küster, Gustav 142, 174, 186, 289, 291, 293-294
Schneider, R. 173
Scholz, A. 293
School of Slavonic and East European Studies 185
Schroth, H. 156
Schwartz, S. 148
Schwarz, R. 184, 188
Secretariado Latino Americano de la Internacional Socialista 173
Segall, D. 182, 185
Segall, Fr. 136, 140
Seitz, E. 153, 181
Seitz, K. 103
Seoung Soo Kim 156
Sharf, A. 148
Shils, Edward 140, 173, 175, 185
Sidorsky, D. 148
Silone, Ignazio 151
Silva, Colvin R. de 146-147
Simecek, H. 138
Sinclair, L.J. 185
Singer, M. 148, 169, 179, 181, 184-185, 188, 290, 294
Singhal, D.P. 173-174, 178-179, 185
Sjahrir, Soetan 142
Sjahruzak, Djohan 147
Smejkal, P. 20
Social Democratic Federation of the U.S.A. 173
Social Democratic Party of Japan 173
" Socialist Affairs" 188, 294
"The Socialist Courier". Organ of the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party 176
The Socialist International (S.I.) 137-143, 173-188, 293
Socialist Party of Japan 289
Socialist Party - Social Democratic Federation of New York City 175, 180
Socialist Union of Central Eastern Europe 186
Sokoll, B. 290
Solari, J.A. 178
Solle, Z. 185
Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands 171, 174, 179-180, 182, 185
Sozialdemokratische Partei der Schweiz 173
Die Sozialgerichtsbarkeit 172
Sozialistische Partei Oesterreichs 179, 183, 188
Sozialistische Jugend Deutschlands 140
Sozialistischer Club Griechenland 179
Speiser, P. 103
Speiser, Wolfgang 138
Spitz, L. 174
S.P.Ö. Frauen Zentral Komitee 136
Sprinzak, Joseph 139
Stampfer, Friedrich 139, 173-175
"The Statesman" 177
Steel, Anth. 177
Steinemann, E. 153
Steiner, H. 180-181, 184-185, 290
Steiner, Senta G. 188
Steuermann, J. 137
Stojakovic, Milan 155
Stolper, T. 173, 181-182, 184-187, 294
Stolz, G. 151
Stössinger, Felix 140
Strasser, Isa 179-180
Sturmthal, Adolf 175
Sudeten Social Democratic Association 181
Sugar, W. 188
Sunday Times Publications Ltd. 289
Sun Pao - Kang 180-181
Surrey Dane, W. 153
Sutherland 104
Suwirio 147
Sveriges Socialdemokratiska Arbetareparti 159
Sweet, P. 137-140, 172, 174-176, 178, 181, 290, 294
Szur, L. 156
T
Tel-Aviv University 188
Telegraf 186, 293
Thankin Chit Maung 147
" Thank You Britain" Fund 181, 183, 186, 188
Thomas, F. 156
Thomas, N. 173, 182
Thomas, T. 185-186
Thomas Nelson and Sons Ltd. 184, 289, 291, 293
Thomson Publications Ltd. 289
Thonet, H.M. 141
Tiden 172
Times 143
Tober, H. 182
Tofahrn, P. 155-156
Tougouchi, M. 151
Trades Union Congress 161
Treves, L. 154, 157, 160, 179, 182
Treves, P. 141, 154
Tribune 139, 186, 188
Trotnow, H. 188
Troy, Sam. Parker 159
U
U Hla Aung 146-147
U Kyaw Nyein 142
Ulitz, E. 293
U.N.E.S.C.O. 173
Ungar, R. 103, 142, 174
University of East Anglia 180, 182
University of Sheffield 183
University of Texas 185
V
Valiani, Leo 139, 143, 167, 173, 289
Vannini, G. 143
Veitch, S.O. 156
Verein für Geschichte der Arbeiterbewegung 184, 186, 188
Vereinigung Deutscher Sozialdemokraten in Grossbritannien 136, 174, 178, 181
Verlag Chmielorz GmbH 174
Verlag der Wiener Volksbuchhandlung 181, 186, 290
Verlag J.H.W. Dietz GmbH 173, 182, 289, 291, 293
Verlag Jungbrunnen 178
Victor Gollancz Ltd. 173, 177-179, 182, 186
Vladan, P.D. 155
Vogel, Hans 104
Voinea, E. 164
Voinea, Serban 141, 154-155, 172-173
Volman, S. 176
Vos, H. 151-152, 155, 181-182, 187-188
Vries, P. de 156
W
Wace, M. 177
Waeger-Adler, A. 290
Wagner, M. 103
Waites, B.A. 187
Waldbrunner, Karl 183
Warmisham, E. 173
Waterlow, J. 174
Watson, S. 143
Watts, S. 173
Weckerle-Geck, K. 153
Weichmann, H. 154
Weinroth, H. 183
Weitzman, D. 180
Weltsch, R. 182, 188
" Weltweite Partnerschaft" 182
Werner, M.E. 181-182
Westdeutscher Rundfunk 182
Wheeler, R. 184
Wickremesinghe, C.E.L. 147
Wiebe 293
Wigham, J. 138
Wijono 146, 173, 180
Wilhelm, K. 177
Williams, Ph. M. 188
Winkler, Ernst 172, 183-184
Wirkner, R. 142
Wodak, W. 136
World Campaign for the Release of South African Political Prisoners 181
World Federation of Trade Unions 155
Y
Yamaguchi, F. 289
Younger, K. 173
Z
Zander, W. 148
Zeisel, H. 175
Zofka, B. 155
Zoysa, M.P. de 156
"Die Zukunft" 174-175, 181, 184-185, 187-188, 290, 294
Geographic Names
Austria
Themes
Socialist and social democrat parties/Socialist International; Exiles/Political refugees; Political prisoners/Political trials
Material Type
Archival material
Persons
Abramovič, Rafail; Adler, Friedrich; Adler, Victor; Bauer, Otto; Kautsky, Karl
Organizations
International Socialist Forum; Socialist International
- I. ALGEMEEN
  - Biografische gegevens (nr. 1-9)
    - Stukken betr. de strafzaak tegen Braunthal beschuldigd wegens hoogverraad., 1934.; 1; 1 omslag
    - Stukken betr. de pogingen van Braunthal om een visum voor Engeland te verkrijgen ten behoeve van zijn familie., 1939.; 2; 1 omslag
    - Stukken betr. Braunthals verzoek om toestemming voor de vestiging van zijn vrouw, zoon en schoonmoeder in Engeland., 1939-1940.; 3; 1 omslag
    - Korrespondentie betr. de pogingen om aan werk te komen., 1939-1949.; 4; 1 omslag
    - Stukken betr. de internering van zijn zoon Friedrich Gustav Braunthal., 1940.; 5; 3 stukken
    - Stukken betr. de internering van zijn zoon Thomas Otto Braunthal., 1941, 1942.; 6; 3 stukken
    - Rekeningen en korrespondentie over financiële aangelegenheden van de familie Braunthal., 1942-1950.; 7; 1 omslag